<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: jquery | P3 Programmer]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.tamizhvendan.in/blog/categories/jquery/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.tamizhvendan.in/"/>
  <updated>2015-05-15T17:54:33+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://blog.tamizhvendan.in/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Tamizhvendan S]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[tamizh88@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DropDownList manipulation using jQuery]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.tamizhvendan.in/blog/2011/02/10/in-this-blog-we-are-going-to-see-how/"/>
    <updated>2011-02-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://blog.tamizhvendan.in/blog/2011/02/10/in-this-blog-we-are-going-to-see-how</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="post">
    <div>
        <p>
            In this blog post we are going to see how can we manipulate a dropdownlist using <a href="http://www.amazon.com/jQuery-Action-Second-Bear-Bibeault/dp/1935182323?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=bor0b-20&amp;link_code=btl&amp;camp=213689&amp;creative=392969" target="_blank">jQuery</a><img alt="" border="0" height="1px" src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=bor0b-20&amp;l=btl&amp;camp=213689&amp;creative=392969&amp;o=1&amp;a=1935182323" style="border-bottom: medium none; border-left: medium none; border-right: medium none; border-top: medium none; margin: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px! important; padding-left: 0px! important; padding-right: 0px! important; padding-top: 0px! important;" width="1px" />. Here is the brief overview what we are exactly going to do.<br />
        </p>
        <ol>
            <li>Dynamically populating the dropdownlist</li>
            <li>Handling the item change event of a dropdownlist</li>
            <li>Getting the value and the text of the dropdownlist selected item</li>
            <li>Programmatically setting the item of the dropdownlist</li>
        </ol>

        <h3>1. Dynamically populating the dropdownlist</h3>

        {% gist 7fd57f06e15b77c58d49 documentInit.js %}
	
        {% gist 7fd57f06e15b77c58d49 layout.html %}
	
        <p>
            The function loadDropDownList will take a collection (a key-value pair array) and populate the dropdownlist “countries”. “$.each” is a jQuery function which iterates the array item by item and calls the “function(index,value)” for each item where index would be the item’s key and value would be the item’s value. Then the list item html markup is created for the list item and appended to the dropdownlist
        </p>

        <h3>2. Handling the item change event of a dropdownlist</h3>
        {% gist 7fd57f06e15b77c58d49 handleChange.js %}
        <p>
            The jQuery API offers lot of useful functions to operate with the html form elements. One of such function is “change()” which will called whenever the item value is get changed.
        </p>
        <h3>3. Getting the value and the text of the dropdownlist selected item</h3>
        {% gist 7fd57f06e15b77c58d49 listChange.js %}
        {% gist 7fd57f06e15b77c58d49 newLayout.html %}
        <p>The jQuery code mentioned above will set the two span labels “countryValue” and “countryText” with the value and text of the selected item in the “countries” dropdownlist, when we select an item in the “countries” dropdownlist. The jQuery function “val()” enable us to find out the value of a form element, in our case we have utilized it to get the value of the “countries” dropdownlist. To get the selected item’s text we have to use the child and attribute selector together as a selector. “#countries &gt; option[value='IN']” – will selects all option child elements(with appropriate value) of item with the id “countries”. “html()” retrieves the html of the selected element. “text(value)” will set the text of the selector.</p>
        <h3>4. Programmatically setting the item of the dropdownlist</h3>
        {% gist 7fd57f06e15b77c58d49 btnClick.js %}

        <h2>Demo</h2>
        <iframe width="100%" height="300" src="http://jsfiddle.net/uE78v/2/embedded/" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" frameborder="0"></iframe>

    </div>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creating a webpage like iGoogle using jQuery]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.tamizhvendan.in/blog/2011/02/07/creating-webpage-like-igoogle-using/"/>
    <updated>2011-02-07T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://blog.tamizhvendan.in/blog/2011/02/07/creating-webpage-like-igoogle-using</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="post">
    <div>
        <p>Would you like to create a webpage like <a href="http://www.igoogleportal.com/portal/index.php">iGoogle</a>??
        This blog post is for you!!</p>

        <p>I hope you are aware of the following stuffs which are the building blocks of this blog post.</p>
        <ol>
            <li>
                <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Head-First-HTML-CSS-XHTML/dp/059610197X?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=bor0b-20&amp;link_code=btl&amp;camp=213689&amp;creative=392969" target="_blank">HTML </a>
            </li>
            <li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/CSS-Missing-David-Sawyer-McFarland/dp/0596802447?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=bor0b-20&amp;link_code=btl&amp;camp=213689&amp;creative=392969" target="_blank">CSS</a><img alt="" border="0" height="1" src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=bor0b-20&amp;l=btl&amp;camp=213689&amp;creative=392969&amp;o=1&amp;a=0596802447" style="border: none !important; margin: 0px !important; padding: 0px !important;" width="1" /></li>
            <li>
                <a href="http://www.amazon.com/jQuery-Novice-Ninja-Earle-Castledine/dp/0980576857?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=bor0b-20&amp;link_code=btl&amp;camp=213689&amp;creative=392969" target="_blank">jQuery</a><img alt="" border="0" height="1" src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=bor0b-20&amp;l=btl&amp;camp=213689&amp;creative=392969&amp;o=1&amp;a=0980576857" style="border: none !important; margin: 0px !important; padding: 0px !important;" width="1" />
            </li>
        </ol>
       
        <p>Let us design the page using “Divide and Conquer” Approach. The tasks involved are</p>
        <ol>
            <li>Defining the webpage layout using HTML</li>
            <li>Style the webpage and Widgets(Sample iGoogle Mock up Widgets) using CSS</li>
            <li>Add the drag and drop functionality using jQuery</li>
        </ol>     
        
        <h3>Task 1: Defining the webpage layout using HTML</h3>
        <p>The HTML is very straight forward. Entire webpage contents have been placed inside a div with the id “iGoogle”. Then each column (iGoogle uses three column layout) is defined by a div element with the id representing the corresponding columns. These columns act as a placeholder for Widgets. Each widget defined as a div element which contains two div elements inside it which represents the header and the body of the Widgets<br />
        </p>
        {% gist 8cc8e2868203484754b1 %}

        <h3>Task 2: Style the webpage and widgets</h3>
        <p>Now we have the HTML Layout ready. Our next task would be applying style to the webpage and the widgets using CSS.</p>
        {% gist e841e3643400836bd57f %}

        <h3>Task 3:  Add the drag and drop functionality using jQuery</h3>
        <p>jQuery offers a rich set of functionality which can be implemented by less lines of coding. With jQuery you can “write less and do more”.  All you need to refer the jQuery API files in your javascript and make use of the functionality it provides. To implement the drag and drop functionality we need the following jQuery library files which can be downloaded from the locations mentioned in the “src” attribute</p>
        {% gist afd522c53a67db5e497b %}

	<p>Now we have the necessary jQuery libraries to implement the drag and drop functionality and all set for implementing the drag and drop support. Here is the code part which implements the drag and drop functionality.</p>

        {% gist 20061eca688b51e73df8 %}

    <p>Yes!! That’s it!! Just three function calls and seven lines of coding!! Now you can drag and drop the widgets and play!!  </p>

        <p>Well, let me explain the jQuery code</p>

        <p>The jQuery UI Sortable plugin makes selected elements sortable by dragging with the mouse. Here in our case the selected elements refer to “column1, column2, colum3” which are the placeholders of the widgets. This sortable plugin has many optional arguments which define how drag and drop should be done. </p>
        <p>
            “connectWith” option allows drag and drop between the columns. i.e., Elements (Widgets in our case) inside the column1 or column2 or column3 can be dragged and dropped on column1 or column2 or column3. 
        </p>
        <p>“handle” option specifies the element which can be used to drag the widget between the columns. “opacity” option defines the transparency of the widget while dragging.  The “disableSelection()” function disable text selection in a widget which often occur while dragging a mouse across a widget. Reference: http://docs.jquery.com/UI/Sortable</p>

        <h5>Summary:</h5>
        To keep the blog post simple, I didn’t implement the persistence of the widget positions. So widgets should not retain its positions when you refresh the page. You can see the source code of this blog post <a href="https://gist.github.com/3632472">here</a>
    </div>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
